Rosa Paula Cuevas

<u>rochiecuevas@gmail.com</u> | 925-844-4768 | Pittsburg 94656 CA LinkedIn: <u>https://linkedin.com/in/rosa-paula-cuevas</u> | GitHub: <u>https://github.com/rochiecuevas</u>

Career Summary

Data and food scientist with 5+ years' experience, seeking to turn information from complex datasets into datadriven quality decisions through proven skills in machine learning, data visualisation, communication, and scientific writing. Achievements include developing regression models to predict rice classification at 94% accuracy and creating a research framework for understanding consumer food choice.

Technical Skills

Languages: R, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, JavaScript

Technical Skills: Web scraping, data processing and visualization (D3, ggplot2, Tableau), statistical analysis

(regression, cluster analyses, random forest, hypothesis testing), database development

Others: MS Excel, MS PowerPoint, MS Word, scientific writing, oral and written communication

Selected Data Science Projects

(SQL, Python, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Tableau)

Natural Language Processing

- Extracting summaries and identifying trends from over 4000 scientific abstracts authored by staff from the International Rice Research Institute (https://enigmatic-plains-87359.herokuapp.com/)
- Keyword extraction, sentiment analysis for poems (https://young-bastion-43943.herokuapp.com/)

Data Visualisation

- Dashboard for belly button microbial diversity (https://still-brook-99773.herokuapp.com/)
- Visualising trends of NY Citi Bike ridership in 2018 (https://rochiecuevas.github.io/Citi Bike/)
- Finding patterns in alien sightings: (https://rochiecuevas.github.io/UFO Sightings/)

Machine Learning

- Exploratory analysis of hotel guest ratings data (https://github.com/janelev/Hotel Rating Analysis)
- Classification of wheat grains into colour classes through logistic regression of spectrometric data

Experience

Data Analytics Consultant, International Rice Research Institute, Philippines (2019–Present)

- Organises data gathered by market researchers, consumer specialists, and anthropologists into databases (using SQL) ready for querying using Python.
- Conducts machine learning techniques, natural language processing/ text mining, and statistical approaches to draw insights from the data sets found in the databases.

Rosa Paula Cuevas

 Leads the development of technical publications on behavioural drivers of food choice in Eastern India.

Scientist, International Rice Research Institute, Philippines (2015–2018)

- Applied <u>machine learning tools</u> (e.g., cluster analyses, random forest, multinomial logistic regression), on R, to model a novel rice classification scheme based on quality attributes.
- Applied natural language processing to develop insights about consumer food choice.
- Collaborated with economists in conducting a <u>hedonic pricing analysis</u> for rice grain quality.

Consultant, International Rice Research Institute, Philippines (2014–2015)

- Acquired descriptive sensory profile data from primary sources and developed the dataset.
- Devised data-driven rice variety recommendations to chefs developing new dishes and menus.

Post-doctoral Fellow, International Rice Research Institute, Philippines (2010–2014)

- Used statistical techniques to identify and analyse <u>starch chemistry</u>—rice quality associations.
- Designed streamlined screening tools for defined rice quality targets with plant breeders.

Professional Service Staff (Contract), International Rice Research Institute, Philippines (2008–2010)

• Developed and implemented a robust MS Access for the GQNC-Quality Evaluation Services' full-cost recovery program.

Education

University of California, Berkeley Extension – San Francisco, CA, USA

Certificate, Data Analytics and Visualisation Boot Camp

University of Queensland – Brisbane, QLD, Australia

PhD Agricultural Science

Doctoral Thesis: Starch microstructure and functional properties in waxy rice (*Orvza sativa* L.)

University of the Philippines Los Banos – Los Banos, Laguna, Philippines

BSc Biology, Magna cum Laude

Thesis: Production and utilisation of crude tylosin from high-yielding *Streptomyces fradiae* NRRL 2702 Mutant No. 93 as therapeutic agent in broilers